a while ago i made a video talking about
the m1 processors and how apple is
optimizing them to be super fast on that
video we also mentioned that apple is
moving away from the x86 or the intel
architecture to the arm architecture and
i ask you to let me know in the comments
if you would like to see the difference
between these architectures in another
video luckily for me many of you said
yes to the question and because i read
all the comments i saw how many upboards
those questions had so we decided to
make a video exactly about that
anonymous nicholas
we are going to talk about the
difference between the x86 or the intel
architecture versus the arm architecture
also we're going to learn why arm was
first popular among mobile devices and
now it's moving to power laptops server
and i don't know if you knew this but
even super computers the top one fastest
supercomputer in the world called the
fugaco in japan is using arm processors
to understand this difference first we
have to learn how the code that
developers write on their keywords is
translated to zeros and ones so let's
get started by first looking at this
very simple piece of c code on this
function called add all we are doing is
creating three number variables called a
b and c
then we say that a is equals to 2 b is
equal to 2 and c is equals to a plus b
that's it that's the code this code will
be executed by the cpu or the central
processing unit of our computer which is
basically the brain the one that knows
all the math and the one that does all
the calculations the problem is that the
code as it is right now cannot be run by
the cpu because the cpu only understands
zeros and ones what we have to do is to
get closer to the processor by
translating our code into a language
that humans can sort of understand and
that processors can easily turn into
zeros and ones into binary code this
transformation of code is called
compilation and the language that we
want to compile to is called assembly
language in assembly language the c code
that we wrote before will be divided
into all the instructions that the
processor needs to follow to run the
code so for example if i wanted to run
that c code in a machine that has a nico
processor let's say then the assembly
language that i will get when i compile
my code will look something like this
and this is just an example this is not
real assembly code but this captures the
essence of what assembly is assembly
code explains literally to the computer
all the steps required for the program
to run in this hypothetical assembly
code that is running in a hypothetical
nico processor we see that our code has
three instructions we have load put and
add
load will reserve a space in memory put
will put a number on that memory address
and add will just add the values on a
memory address now all we have to do is
give this code to the assembler which
turns everything into zeros and ones and
that's it the processor will now be able
to run our code but now we have a
problem because our code was compiled to
be run in a computer with a nico
processor if another user with the intel
processor or amd processor want to run
the code they won't be able to this is
because processors with a different
architecture like intel x86 or arm have
a different isa isa means instruction
set architecture which is basically a
set of commands or instructions that the
processor is able to execute if we want
an intel or an arm processor to be able
to run the code that we saw before we
are going to have to compile that code
again but this time we're gonna have to
make assembly code that uses the
instructions of those specific
processors if we compile that code to be
running an intel architecture for
example we will get an assembly code
that looks something like this if we
compile the code to be run in a arm
architecture which as we know is what
the m1 macbooks have the assembly code
will look something like this now as you
can see they share some instructions
like mob and add but for the most part
they look very different from each other
but the name of the instructions is not
the only thing that makes them different
the most important difference that they
have is the architecture the x86 family
of processors which is what intel air
amd are famous for use something called
the sisk architecture and arm processors
use something called the risk
architecture sisk means complex
instruction set computing and risk means
reduce instructions said computing so
what does that mean what we have to
focus on is the word complex or reduced
as we saw before the processors have a
certain amount of instructions or
commands that they can execute these
instructions and even their name depends
on the designer of the chips cis
processors have more instructions than
risk processors as we saw on the
assembly code before both processors
understand the ad instruction let's say
and also they understand the mull
instruction which do multiplication but
and this is an example where a cis
processor might have a instruction
called power of three let's say a risk
processor might not have that
instruction at all so if i am writing
assembly code for a cis processor and i
need to raise the number to the power of
three let's say i will use the power of
three instructions that the processor
has
but if i am on a risk processor i will
have to manually use the mull
instruction three times to get the same
result in this example with risk it will
take me three steps let's say three
lines of code to do something that would
take me one instruction on a cisc
processor the idea behind risk
processors is that the processor
shouldn't do so much it should not be
able to do so many things instead it
should perform the basic operations
really fast and that is the compromise
in a cisc world with one instruction we
can tell the computer to do something
sort of complex and that might take a
little bit of time or we can send
multiple instructions to a risk
processor that will be executed very
fast now you and me we don't have to
make this compromise because we use
compilers the compiler will generate the
code for us but we have to remember that
before many of the programming languages
that we are used to today were created
legend developers used to write assembly
code by hand whole operative systems
were written in assembly and developers
as they do today care about writing as
little code as possible so if you were
writing code for a cisc processor it
would have been better because the
processor gives you so many shortcuts
and commands that a risk processor
wouldn't have and also and it's
important to remember this back then
computers didn't have a lot of ram
memory and when you open a program and
you want to run some code and that
program has to be copied into the raw
memory to be executed by the processor
now that means that if you write a lot
of code and your program is very big
there is more memory needed to be able
to run your program so when computers
didn't have a lot of ram memory and when
developers used to actually write
assembly code by hand it made a lot of
sense to use cisc processors because
they had so many shortcuts and so many
helper commands for developers but now
we have compilers and memory ram is
abundant it's really cheap and nobody or
almost nobody is writing assembly code
by hand but the thing that people care
about most these days is battery life we
must consider that the more complex
instructions the processor is able to
process the more energy it will need to
run and this is what made arm and risk
architecture processors so popular among
mobile devices because battery life is
one of the most important things arm
processors are incredibly energy
efficient also because risk processors
don't have as many features as cis
processors they require less transistors
and that means they are cheaper to make
and also they take up less space in 1985
an arm processor had 25 000 transistors
compared to
275 000 transistors from my intel
processor on the same year and it was in
1990 when apple picked up on this and
asked the arm makers acorn to license
the technology to use it on their apple
newton then nokia started to use arm as
well and since then more and more mobile
and internet of things devices use arm
but now you might be wondering why
people still use sisk if risk is so good
if you look online and you ask people
around the consensus seems to be that
the difference between sisk and risk is
sort of blurry nowadays they both have
learned from each other and implemented
the best of each other's features arm
has implemented many extra instructions
like this one for example that does
javascript type conversion so for some
people arm is looking more like cisc and
also some x86 processors have included
some risk features as well so the answer
is not really as black and white as we
would like we also have to think about
backwards compatibility intel with the
x86 cisc architecture has been around
for a very long time there is a lot of
software computers servers banks
government that are running on software
that runs on the x86 architecture so the
reason why we still use cisc could be
because we have always been using cis
because the transition between x86 to
arm is not painless there are still
today m1 users that cannot run some
programs because the developers need to
do some adjustments to the code to turn
them from x86 to arm but that is
changing as we know and it's also thanks
i believe to the business model that the
arm company has arm company doesn't make
the chips unlike intel intel makes the
chips they have the factories arm mostly
licenses the ip the intellectual
property this means that other companies
can use the arm ideas of course after
they pay and they can make chips and
processors customized to their needs
this is what apple is doing they are
using the arm technology but they are
customizing and optimizing their chips
for their use case which is their
computers this way they can have more
speed running mac os and they get better
battery life and they don't have to wait
for intel to innovate this is also what
amazon is doing actually aws is now
promoting their new graviton servers
that are running on a custom made arm
processor that are said to be 10 to 20
percent cheaper and perform 40
faster than intel or amd servers again
this makes sense because amazon knows
exactly where a server should be
optimized so they can use arm and
optimize their chip for their server use
case even microsoft is starting to
design their own arm based system on a
chips for their next surface laptops so
to conclude today we saw the difference
between the risk and the cis
architecture in theory but the truth is
that on the implementation in the real
world the lines seem to be very blurry
on my part i'm happy to know that thanks
to arm the server costs are going down
and the speed is going up that it's
awesome and also i'm happy because there
is competition and that means that the
consumer is the one that will win at the
end thank you so much for watching this
video and thank you for leaving the
comments on the previous video because
this is why we made this video today
because of you i know what ideas to make
and i know what you want to watch so if
there is something else you want to
launch please let me know in the
comments i'm going to be reading them
right now and also if you like the way i
explain things and you want to learn to
code for free then please check out our
website we have many courses they are
for free and you can learn javascript
react react native python many other
things for free with explanations like
this one thank you so much again stay
happy stay free eat kimchi we love you
have something here see you on the next
one bye